Inventory of the Brown, Coalter, Tucker Papers (I) 1780-1929
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Group C: John Thompson Brown Papers, 1816-1839., 6 boxes. (Box 14-19)
  - Box 18 - Correspondence of John Thompson Brown: The party spirit of 1834-1835; exchange of blows over political questions in this period. Manuscript of a speech on the death of Lafayette; two notebooks relating to Virginia laws which concerned Brown as Chairman of the Finance Committee of the Ho
    - John Thompson Brown. Draft of a speech delivered in Petersburg on the occasion of the death of Lafayette, 9 July 1834., 43 pages. ADrS. (Box-folder 18:14)
      Endorsed: "To my sons, should they ever read it."
    - Edward J. Steptoe, West Point, to his uncle, John Thompson Brown, 11 August 1834. (Box-folder 18:15)
      Report of his progress at the U.S. Military Academy.
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Peronneau Finley, 8 November 1834. (Box-folder 18:16)
      Draft of a letter sending condolences for the death of a sister and congratulations on the birth of a son.
    - William Cabell Rives, Washington, D.C., to John Thompson Brown, December 1834., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 18:17)
      His resignation from the U.S. Senate.
    - John Thompson Brown, Richmond, to Mrs. Mary E. Brown, December 1834., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 18:18)
      "No subject arouses anybody except the senatorial election."
    - John Thompson Brown, Richmond, to Henry Brown, Jr., 17 December 1834. (Box-folder 18:19)
      He offers to place all his monetary resources at the service of his brother in his new business venture.
    - John Thompson Brown, Richmond, to Henry Brown, Jr., January 1835., 3 letters, 1 draft. ALS, ADrS. (Box-folder 18:20)
      On the 17th he prepared a draft of a letter, which he sent on the 20th, giving an account of a fight in the halls of the General Assembly between himself and John Hampden Pleasants.
    - John Hampden Pleasants to John Thompson Brown, 17 January 1835. (Box-folder 18:21)
      A letter of apology for the battle fought in the halls of the Virginia Capitol.
    - John Thompson Brown, Richmond, to Mrs. Mary E. Brown, 29 January 1835. (Box-folder 18:22)
      An account of his speech which was "better received than anything I have ever made."
    - Speech of John Thompson Brown of Petersburg upon the Election of a Senator in Congress: Delivered in the House of Delegates of Virginia, 29 January 1835., 28 pages. PB. (Box-folder 18:23)
      Points out the importance of this election for "future political events and party combinations in the state," and defends the incumbent, Mr. Leigh.
    - John Thompson Brown, Richmond, to Mrs. Mary E. Brown, [January] 1835. (Box-folder 18:24)
    - John Thompson Brown. "Notes and References on Virginia Statutes at Large," [1838]., 70 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 18:25)
      Prepared for use in the Finance Committee of the House of Deputies.
    - John Thompson Brown. "A common-place Book of Notes and References 'quae reconderet duta que promeret'," [1838]., 116 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 18:26)
      Notes on taxes, license fees, and the like, prepared by John Thompson Brown for use on the Finance Committee of the House of Delegates.
  - Box 19 - Correspondence of John Thompson Brown from February 1835, until his death in November 1836; manuscripts of four articles written to oppose the candidacy of Martin Van Buren for President, 1835-1839, n.d., 104 items. (Box-folder 19:1-47)
    The closing sessions of the State Legislature of 1834-1835 are reported in the letters at the beginning of this box. The party spirit runs high in Petersburg as the "Jackson party" opposes John Thompson Brown (March 1835). He is involved in a street fight with an opponent in which he receives a black eye, but the argument is made up after he wins the election (April 1835).
    Before the next session of the legislature, John Thompson Brown is occupied in collecting more material on the question of slavery (August 1835), and prepared three long drafts written in opposition to the candidacy of Martin Van Buren for President of the U.S. Undated drafts of notes on legal cases are included at the end of the 1835 section.
    Henry Brown, Jr., the brother of John Thompson Brown, died in May 1836, while on a buying trip to Philadelphia and New York for his Lynchburg store. The trip of John Thompson Brown to meet the body of his brother, and his activity in settling his brother's affairs in Lynchburg are reported in the letters included in this box.
    At the end of July he takes his family to his father's home, Otter Hills, near New London in Campbell County, for the funeral sermon of Henry Brown, Jr. While there he contracts an illness which keeps him there until his death on 26 November 1836.
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to his brother, Henry Brown, Jr., 6 February 1835. (Box-folder 19:1)
      Announces the birth of a son, John Thompson Brown II, and tells his brother that he had ordered $2800 placed to his account to support the store that he had opened.
    - John Thompson Brown, Richmond, to his wife, Mrs. Mary E. Brown, February-March 1835., 6 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 19:2)
      Political activity in Petersburg.
    - John Thompson Brown, Richmond, to Henry Brown, Jr., March 1835., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 19:3)
      "The Jackson party has brought out the most popular man in Petersburg against...it is quite likely he will beat me."
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Henry Brown, Jr., April 1835., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 19:4)
      On April 18 he writes, "I was elected by a majority of 37 (13 of which were from Richmond)." There is also a report of a street fight between John Thompson Brown and "a Jackson man."
    - John Hampden Pleasants, Richmond, to John Thompson Brown, 16 May 1835. (Box-folder 19:5)
      Concerning the chances of Van Buren to carry Virginia in the election.
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Henry Brown, Jr., 6 June 1835. (Box-folder 19:6)
      Plans to retire from politics and seek a position as Judge of the courts.
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Samuel T. Brown, June-July 1835. (Box-folder 19:7)
      He has sent a box of books to help him in his law studies, and describes a visit by his old friend Peronneau Finley and his family.
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Henry Brown, 8 August 1835. (Box-folder 19:8)
      Writes to his father about plans to visit him.
    - Drafts on the subject of the northern resolutions on slavery, particularly those recently passed in Portland and Boston, 25 August 1835., 3 items. ALS. (Box-folder 19:9)
    - Notes on slavery, n.d., 4 items. ADr. (Box-folder 19:10)
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Henry Brown, Jr., October-November 1835., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 19:11)
      Family discussion, especially concerned with the sisters who were yet to find husbands.
    - Carter N. Berkeley, and others, University of Virginia, to John Thompson Brown, 26 October 1835. (Box-folder 19:12)
      Notice of the election of John Thompson Brown as an honorary member of the Jefferson Society.
    - Undated Drafts, n.d. (Box-folder 19:13-18)
      - An act to extend the 1834 acts concerning slaves, free Negroes and mulattoes, etc., [1835]. (Box-folder 19:13)
      - Notes for a speech on the stand of Mr. Van Buren on emancipation, [1835]., 28 numbered columns. ADrS. (Box-folder 19:14)
        Signed "Mr. Brown."
      - Notes entitled "Acts, not Professions, the index of Truth," [1835]., 11 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 19:15)
      - Notes entitled "No. 2. Acts, not Professions, the test of Truth," also an additional 2 page insertion, [1835]., 12, 2 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 19:16)
      - Notes entitled "No. 3. Acts, not Professions, the test of truth," [1835]., 48 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 19:17)
        This series of drafts is in opposition to Martin Van Buren, candidate for the President of the United States.
      - Undated legal drafts of John Thompson Brown, n.d., 9 items. ADr. (Box-folder 19:18)
    - " H[ouse] of D[elegates]...Mr. Brown of Petersburg said...," 16 January 1836., 6 pages. (Box-folder 19:19)
    - A page from The Southern Literary Messenger, Vol. II, No. 3, February 1836. (Box-folder 19:20)
    - Address of the Anti-Van Buren Members of the General Assembly... to the People of Virginia, 16 March 1836., 15 pages. (Box-folder 19:21)
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Henry Brown, 30 March 1836. (Box-folder 19:22)
      Good reports of the new business venture of his brother, Henry Brown, Jr.
    - John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Henry Brown, Jr., 8 April 1836. (Box-folder 19:23)
      To his brother, on a buying trip to New York; political prospects now look bright, but "the state is lost" to the Anti-Van Buren forces.
    - Commission as Captain in the Cavalry of the Virginia Militia of John Thompson Brown, 20 April 1836. (Box-folder 19:24)
      Signed by Wyndham Robertson.
    - Constitution and By-laws of the Petersburg light Dragoons, signed Capt. John Thompson Brown, 1836. (Box-folder 19:25)
    - John Thompson Brown, Hobson's Inn, Homes, Otter Hills, and Lynchburg, to Mrs. Mary E. Brown, May-June 1836., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 19:26)
      On the trip to accompany his sister-in-law and the body of Henry Brown, Jr. back to the family home, Otter Hills. Henry Brown, Jr. died while on a shopping trip to New York for supplies for his Lynchburg store.
    - Ann Maury, New York, to Mrs. John Thompson Brown, 20 May 1836. (Box-folder 19:27)
      The body of Henry Brown, Jr. was taken that morning for Virginia.
    - John Thompson Brown, near New London, to his niece, Maria C. Brown, at the Academy of the Visitation, Georgetown, D.C., 31 May 1836. (Box-folder 19:28)
      On the death of her father, Henry Brown Brown, Jr.
    - John Thompson Brown, Lynchburg, to Mrs. Mary E. Brown, June 1836., 6 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 19:29)
      Taking inventory at the store of his late brother; preparing to settle his estate.
    - John Thompson Brown, Lynchburg, to Henry Brown, June-July 1836., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 19:30)
      Reports on the stocktaking in the store of Henry Brown, Jr. On July 19 he wrote that he was coming to his father's place on the Sunday next to hear his brother's funeral preached. This is the last letter from John Thompson Brown to his father, for on that visit to Otter Hills he was taken with the illness from which he died.
    - John Thompson Brown, Lynchburg, to his sister, Miss Frances Brown, Otter Hills, June 1836. (Box-folder 19:31)
      On the disposal of the store inventory; sends a piano to her.
    - John Thompson Brown, Lynchburg, to Mrs. Mary E. Brown, 2 July 1836. (Box-folder 19:32)
      Mourning his brother's death, he makes arrangements for his own family to join him. (This is the last letter written by John Thompson Brown preserved in this collection.)
    - Maria Carter Brown, Georgetown, D.C., to John Thompson Brown, 5 July l836. (Box-folder 19:33)
      The niece of John Thompson Brown writes to her uncle regarding the recent death of her father, Henry Brown, Jr.
    - K. B. Townley, Lynchburg, to John Thompson Brown, 15 August 1836. (Box-folder 19:34)
      A Quaker associate of Henry Brown, Jr. writes regarding the settling of the store business.
    - K. B. Townley, Lynchburg, to John Thompson Brown, 21 October 1836. (Box-folder 19:35)
    - "The sermon...preached at the funeral of the late John T. Brown," [November] 1836., 36 pages. AD. (Box-folder 19:36)
      Enclosures: "A lock of the hair of John Thompson Brown, 29 years"; envelope marked, "For sister Mary from my dear brother John's Grave, Nov. 13th, 1845, [Mrs.] A[lice Brown] Worthington," with clover leaves inside.
    - "A copy of the proceedings of a Meeting of the Petersburg Light Dragoons," signed Robt. B. Bolling, Chairman, 24 November 1836. (Box-folder 19:37)
      A resolution in memory of John Thompson Brown.
    - "Memorial Resolution by the Mayor, Aldermen and Commality of the Town of Petersburg to John Thompson Brown," 26 November 1836. (Box-folder 19:38)
      Signed D. M. Bernard, Clerk. Endorsement by James MacFarland, Jr., to Mrs. John Thompson Brown.
    - Ann Maury, New York, to Mrs. John Thompson Brown, 29 November 1836. (Box-folder 19:39)
      Condolences on the death of her husband.
    - "Tribute of Respect, Nassau Hall, Princeton...In behalf of the Cliosophic Society, Wm. A. Dod," 5 December 1836. (Box-folder 19:40)
      A resolution that the members wear the usual badge of mourning for thirty days in honor of John Thompson Brown.
    - George W. Munford, House of Delegates, to Henry Brown, Esq., 5 December 1836. (Box-folder 19:41)
      A copy of the unanimous resolution of the House of Delegates in memory of John Thompson Brown.
    - Four calling cards of John Thompson Brown, n.d., 4 items. (Box-folder 19:42)
    - Mrs. Mary E. Brown, widow of John Thompson Brown, Petersburg, to Henry Brown, 27 January 1837. (Box-folder 19:43)
      A letter of grief written by Mrs. Brown to her father-in-law.
    - M. W. Garnett to Mrs. Mary E. Brown, 9 March 1837. (Box-folder 19:44)
    - Court document to Henry Brown and Mrs. Mary E. Brown, Executors of John Thompson Brown, March 1839. (Box-folder 19:45)
    - John Thompson Brown Papers. Undated drafts, n.d. (Box-folder 19:46a-n)
      - Manuscript notebook, n.d., 40 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 19:46a)
        Includes: A dramatic sketch, Kentucky Land Laws, Goosawattee Indians, and map of the region around Bedford, Virginia
      - "Concerning the summary and unwanted dismissal of W. from his position of Clerk of Court by Judge C.," [pre. 1830]., 16 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 19:46b)
      - "Concerning the problem of instruction to the Senators,", 5 pages. ADr. Incomplete. (Box-folder 19:46c)
      - Notes on Mr. Madison's position on State Rights, n.d. (Box-folder 19:46d)
      - The bounties offered for Indian scalps in Bedford between 1755 and 1758, n.d. (Box-folder 19:46e)
      - Miscellaneous other papers, n.d., 11 items. AD. (Box-folder 19:46f-n)
    - "The draft within is of the Doric order...," n.d. (Box-folder 19:47)
      A large folded ink drawing of a building "taken from the Colonade of the Temple of Minerva Parthenon at Athens," with notes of construction details. Ca. 1830.
  Series 4: Group D
- Group D: Brown and Tucker Papers, 1839-1929., 5 boxes. (Box-folder 20-24)
  Papers of John Thompson Brown, Colonel of 1st Regiment Virginia Artillery who was killed in action in 1864. Included are letters concerning a disagreement with William Nelson Pendleton. Papers also include correspondence of his son, Henry Peronneau Brown and his son's wife Frances Bland (Coalter) Brown as well as newspaper clippings concerning Judge John Randolph Tucker and the correspondence of Cynthia Beverley Tucker Coleman. There are also nineteenth century engravings.
    Subseries 1: Col. John Thompson Brown II
  - Correspondence, commissions, receipts, etc., of Col. John Thompson Brown II, killed in action on 6 May 1864; his drafts of speeches in defense of slavery, 1844-1864., 83 items. (Box 20:1-40)
    This box contains the papers from the period after the death of John Thompson Brown, and concern John Thompson Brown II, born in 1835, some 18 months before the death of his father.
    One letter (20 November 1844) lists the courses studied by boys at the ages of 9, 11, and 13; a travel book gives an interesting picture of Europe (4 May 1857); and a draft of a letter describes the bleedings to which a tourist entering Italy had to submit.
    John Thompson Brown II was elected Second Lieutenant by the members of his company (1 December 1859). Also included are notes of speeches made to rouse war enthusiasm. The receipt for a saber and belt (23 April 1861) mark the beginning of action, and other records follow John Thompson Brown II's rise to Major, then to Colonel. His request for a transfer to a more active field of war and an extended argument with his commanding officer, Brig. Gen. William Nelson Pendleton, are of interest. The box concludes with items which appear to have been on the person of Col. John Thompson Brown II, when he was killed in action on 6 May 1864.
    - John Thompson Brown II, Petersburg, to his "Aunt Lockie" [Brown Irvine], 20 November 1844. (Box-folder 20:1)
      Lists the courses in school taken by a nine year old boy and his two brothers, Wilicox, 11 years old, and P[eronneau], 13 years old.
    - Travel notebook, unsigned, 4 May 1857., 58 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 20:2)
    - A report of "repeated bleeding in Italy," n.d. (Box-folder 20:3)
    - Promissory note, N. M. Lewis to Wm. J. Chick, 1 January 1859. (Box-folder 20:4)
    - Thomas P. August, Col. 1st Reg., Virginia Volunteers, 1 December 1859. (Box-folder 20:5)
      Certifies that John Thompson Brown II was elected Second Lieutenant by viva voce vote of the members of his company.
    - Draft of Speech in favor of the Southern position, [1860]. (Box-folder 20:6)
      References to Douglas and the threat to slavery.
    - Draft of speech opposing abolition, [1860]., 5 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 20:7)
      Concerns the raid on Harper's Ferry by John Brown, 19 October 1859, and the treatment of him as a martyr in the North.
    - Speech at the dedication of an Armory, [1861]. (Box-folder 20:8)
      "I greatly fear that the time has passed when great questions of State equality are to be settled in the Halls of Congress...this settlement requires powder and ball..."
    - M. C. Selant and Co. bill for coal to John Thompson Brown II, 5 January 1861. (Box-folder 20:9)
    - H. R. Pleasants and John Thompson Brown II, receipt for sabre and belt from Geo. W. Randolph, Capt., 1st Reg., Virginia Volunteers, 23 April 1861., 2 copies. ADS. (Box-folder 20:10)
    - Bills rendered to Capt. John Thompson Brown II and his Company, May 1861., 3 items. AD. (Box-folder 20:11)
    - J. H. Sands, Young's Mill, to Major John Thompson Brown II, at Young's Farm, 6 October 1861. (Box-folder 20:12)
      Report on ammunition on hand.
    - Receipts for pay and supplies for Col. John Thompson Brown II, January-May 1862., 3 items. ADS. (Box-folder 20:13)
    - C. H. D. Chine, Poe's Farm, to [of the Court], and Corp. M. Terrell to the Court, 19 June 1862., 2 items. ADS. (Box-folder 20:14)
      Court Martial action taken for refusal to do guard duty, by a trooper under the command of Col. John Thompson Brown II.
    - Receipts for horses and supplies, June-September 1862., 4 items. ADS. (Box-folder 20:15)
    - Col. John Thompson Brown II to Brig. Genl. William Nelson Pendleton, 29 September 1862. (Box-folder 20:16)
      Request for transfer, with his command, to the Division of Gen. D. H. Hills, so that he might be more actively engaged.
    - Receipt and lists of stores, October 1862., 3 items. AD. (Box-folder 20:17)
    - Draft of a suggestion for winter furloughs in order to extend the length of service in the fighting season, [1862]., 6 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 20:18)
    - Map of the State of Virginia, published by West and Johnson, Richmond, 1862. (Box-folder 20:19)
    - Receipts for Ordnance stores, January 1863., 4 items. ADS. (Box-folder 20:20)
    - R. P. Rides to Col. John Thompson Brown II, 1 February 1863. (Box-folder 20:21)
      Concerning the families of the officers.
    - Receipts for horses, mules, and supplies, February-April 1863., 13 items. ADS. (Box-folder 20:22)
    - Col. John Thompson Brown II, to Brig. Gen. William Nelson Pendleton, 3 June 1863. (Box-folder 20:23)
      Concerning a dispute arising between the two over John Thompson Brown's command.
    - Special Order No. 154, signed by W. H. Taylor and Brig. Gen. William Nelson Pendleton, 8 June 1863., 4 items. (Box-folder 20:24)
    - Exchange of letters between John Thompson Brown II and Brig. Gen. William Nelson Pendleton, August 1863., 4 items. ALS. (Box-folder 20:25)
    - Receipts for supplies by Col. John Thompson Brown II, November-December 1863., 4 items. ADS. (Box-folder 20:26)
    - Receipt for whitewashing 2 rooms to Mrs. Brown by John M. Godwin, 1863. (Box-folder 20:27)
    - Col. John Thompson Brown II, to Lt. Col. William Nelson Taylor, 11 March 1864. (Box-folder 20:28)
      Request the return of his report on the battle of Chancellorsville so that he might submit it to Gen. Stuart.
    - Receipts and accounts regarding provisions for the Howitzer Companies, April 1864., 4 items. ADS. (Box-folder 20:29)
    - Papers which appear to have been on the person of John Thompson Brown II, when he was killed in action, 6 May 1864. (Box-folder 20:30-37)
      - Gift list and cover addressed to Jackson's Reserve Artillery, near Bowling Green, Caroline County, n.d. (Box-folder 20:30)
      - Commission Book, containing several commissions, leather bound, n.d. (Box-folder 20:31)
      - Commission from the Commonwealth of Virginia, n.d. (Box-folder 20:32)
      - Receipt for supplies, n.d. (Box-folder 20:33)
      - Blank pay account documents, n.d., 2 copies. PM. (Box-folder 20:34)
      - Printed calling cards of John Thompson Brown in cover, n.d. (Box-folder 20:35)
      - Two leather pocket packets, n.d. (Box-folder 20:36)
      - Terrain map, n.d. (Box-folder 20:37)
    - Newspaper obituaries of Col. John Thompson Brown II, May 1864., 5 items. NCl. (Box-folder 20:38)
    - "In Memory of John Thompson Brown," autograph poem and newspaper text; "Lines written on seeing 'Rifle' the war-horse of Col. J. T. B...." from the Richmond Dispatch, 6 May 1864., 3 items. (Box-folder 20:39)
    - A marker. "Thompson Brown" with blue ribbons attached, [1864]. (Box-folder 20:40)
    Subseries 2: Henry Peronneau Brown
  - Letters to Henry Peronneau Brown, oldest son of the Hon. John Thompson Brown, written by his widowed mother, Mrs. Mary E. Brown, of Petersburg; family correspondence after his marriage to Frances Bland Coalter (see also Box 6) in the Civil War and Reconstruction years; twelve letters from John Coalter II, to Mrs. Brown, his sister, illustrating the difficulties in re-establishing a farm in Virginia after the war, 1849-1885., 108 items. (Box 21:1-71)
    Papers relating to the oldest son of John Thompson Brown, Henry Peronneau Brown, begin with letters written by his mother Mrs. Mary E. Brown. She expresses concern that her son is more interested in affairs other than his studies (1 March 1849). His school career is traced briefly through his years at the University of Virginia (28 June 1851).
    The letters exchanged between Henry Peronneau Brown and his fiancee, Frances Baland Coalter, 1858, lead into the family correspondence which completes this box. (Other letters of Frances Bland Coalter and her family are found in Box 6, Coalter and Tucker Papers.)
    From May, 1861, all letters are concerned with the war. Letters written by John Coalter II, to his sister Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown in 1878 give a graphic picture of the struggle made by a southern farmer to re-establish himself after the war.
    - Mrs. Mary E. Brown, Petersburg, to her brother-in-law Samuel T. Brown, Charleston, South Carolina and New London, Virginia, March-October 1849., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:1)
      The widow of John Thompson Brown writes with concern about her oldest son, Peronneau, who is attending school in South Carolina. He was devoting too much time to outdoor affairs of college life and not enough to his studies.
    - Samuel T. Brown, Otter Hills, to Henry Peronneau Brown, 18 April 1850., ALS. (Box-folder 21:2)
      Congratulating him on his success at Charleston College; a proposed biography of John Thompson Brown.
    - Mrs. Alice [Brown] Hogal, Richmond, to Mrs. Mary E. Brown, 17 June 1850. (Box-folder 21:3)
    - Samuel T. Brown, Otter Hills, to Mrs. Mary [E. Brown], 28 June 1851. (Box-folder 21:4)
      Concerning Henry Peronneau Brown, attending the University [of Virginia].